Finding Aid for Wesley W. Hyde Papers, 1902-1913
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wesley W. Hyde papers, 1902-1913
Hyde, Wesley W.
1 linear ft.
851491 Aa 2
Grand Rapids, Michigan, attorney, member of the Michigan Commission on Uniform Legislation, and organizer of the Civic Club of Grand Rapids. Correspondence, speeches, articles and legal documents relating to his interest in municipal reform.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Beal B. Hyde (donor no. 4842 ) and came to the library in 1970. Additional material came from Alexander P. Hyde, MD (donor no. 9570 ) in 2005.
The collection is open to research.
Wesley Hyde was born in Macomb County, Michigan, then moved with his parents to Kent County in 1860. He studied law in his father's office. In August 1875, he was appointed deputy county clerk, then becoming county clerk in 1876 where he served until 1880. Hyde was admitted to the bar in 1877 and began the practice of law in his father's office, subsequently forming partnerships with John W, Stone, then J. Edward Earle, and Edwin F. Uhl.
In 1899, he was appointed member of the State Board of Law Examiners, serving as that body's secretary. In 1903, he was appointed a member of the Michigan Commission on Uniform Legislation.
In 1901, he was one of the organizers of the Civic Club of Grand Rapids.
The Hyde collection is arranged into two series: Correspondence and other Personal Papers; and Speeches and Writings. The collection contains little relating to his legal or other public activities. Much of the correspondence concerns his efforts to have published his volume entitled "Social Guides." His speeches pertain to issues of good government and Grand Rapids municipal reform.
Subjects:
Church and social problems--Michigan.; Civic Club of Grand Rapids (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Lawyers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Michigan. Commission on Uniform Legislation.; Social reformers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Strikes and lockouts--Michigan.
Contributors:
Ballinger, Richard Achilles, 1858-1922.; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; James, William, 1842-1910.; Parmelee, Maurice, 1882-1969.; Pound, Roscoe, 1870-1964.; Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926.; Wilcox, Delos F. (Delos Franklin), 1873-1928.; Willoughby, Westel Woodbury, 1867-1945.
- Correspondence and other Personal Papers
  - Correspondence
    - 1894-1910 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1913 and undated (Box 1)
  - Legal documents (Box 1)
  - Commissions (Box 1)
  - Genealogy (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
- Speeches and writings
  - General, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - "Can We Divorce Municipal Government from National Party Politics?" undated (Box 1)
  - "Private Property in Land" undated (Box 1)
  - "History and Development of Social Science" September 8, 1897 (Box 1)
  - "Autobiography of Andrew Dixon White" read before University Club of Grand Rapids, February 23, 1906 (Box 1)
  - "Municipal Ownership" read before class in Applied Christianity, Fountain Street Baptist Church, December 1906 (Box 1)
  - "Is the Influence of Newspapers and Periodicals Greater for Good or Evil" read before a social science class in the Westminster Presbyterian Church, Spring 1907 (Box 1)
  - "Workmen's Compensation Act" May 18, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of unpublished volume entitled "Social Guides" (Box 1)
Partial Index to Correspondence
Ballinger, Richard Achilles, 1858-1922.
March 11, 1911
Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.
June 9, 1909, June 17, 1909, July 5, 1909
James, William, 1842-1910.
May 17, 1909
Parmelee, Maurice, 1882-1969.
March 6, 1913
Pound, Roscoe, 1870-1964.
February 25, 1913
Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926
January 7, 1910, December 24, 1910, December 31, 1910, January 9, 1911, January 12, 1911
Wilcox, Delos F. (Delos Franklin), 1873-1928.
February 15, 1909, September 7, 1909
Willoughby, Westel Woodbury, 1867-1945.
July 22, 1911